"Can Cold Showers Improve Immune Function?"
Several studies
have demonstrated
that cold temperatures
may be a potential risk factor
for cancer development.
For example, this study
compared the 50 countries
with the highest cancer rates
to the countries
with the lowest cancer rates
and concluded that people
living in cold environments
may have a higher risk
of getting
and dying from cancer.
A similar study
within the United States
found that colder counties
were associated
with a greater cancer incidence.
But couldn't something
like vitamin D exposure
better explain these findings?
Patients diagnosed with cancer
during summer months
may have a better prognosis
than those diagnosed
during the winter.
But again, this could be
because of the sunshine vitamin,
vitamin D.
Evidently, an animal colony
had less cancer
when they moved
from a colder country
to a warmer country
based on some observation
published in 1939.
Seems a bit of a stretch,
but then this study
was published.
Standard housing temperature
for laboratory mice
in research facilities
is mandated to be between
20 and 26 Celsius,
like typical room temperature
in the 70s Fahrenheit.
But, that's chilly for mice,
causing chronic
mild cold stress.
When that stress
is alleviated
by housing
at warmer temperatures,
like in the 80s Fahrenheit
(27 - 32 °C),
researchers observed a striking
reduction in tumor formation,
cancer growth rate,
and metastasis.
Warmer was better.
They suggested
that the cold stress
results in a suppression
of antitumor immunity.
Then, why do they keep mice
at that lower temperature?
It reduces the frequency
of cage cleaning
and helps ensure the thermal
comfort of the staff.
The proposed mechanism
is the activation
of the fight-or-flight response
that leads to the release
of the stress hormone
norepinephrine,
also known as noradrenalin.
Take a dip
in a typical cold plunge,
and there can be a doubling
of norepinephrine levels
in the blood within minutes.
And we don't seem to habituate,
meaning we get that same bump
in norepinephrine
after each cold-water immersion,
even after 3 months
of regular plunges.
Might that be suppressing
immune function?
Or might it instead be hormesis,
that which doesn't kill us
makes us stronger?
Cold-water swimmers
claim to suffer fewer
and milder infections
as a result of the practice.
Even if that's true,
cold-water swimmers
are swimming.
Maybe it's the exercise,
not the cold?
How would we figure this out?
To control for any effect
of swimming,
researchers compared
cold-water swimmers
to indoor heated-pool swimmers
and found no difference
in upper respiratory tract
susceptibility between swimmers
in cold water and heated pools.
Therefore, cold-water swimming
appears to have
no protective effect.
What about regularly
taking cold showers?
Cold showers were first designed
for the purpose
of "treating the insane,"
and then used as an instrument
of torture in prisons
before it started
killing too many people.
Rather than being abandoned,
however,
the shower was transformed
by the use of warm water
to actually clean people.
I had no idea.
If you randomize people
to short daily cold showers
versus hot showers
for a few months,
regular cold shower exposure
does appear to put
the immune system on high alert.
Does that actually translate
into less sickness?
There's only been this one
randomized trial
on The Effect of Cold Showering
on Health and Work:
A Randomized Controlled Trial.
Participants were randomized
to shower as normal,
but end their showers
with 0, 30, 60, or 90 seconds
of cold water.
And compared
to the no cold group,
the different cold-water groups
collectively had a 29% reduction
of self-reported sick leave
from work,
but no fewer self-reported days
of sickness.
So, maybe the cold showering
made them less sick
even though they were sick
for the same duration?
The problem, of course,
is that while
there was a control group,
there was no placebo control.
So, maybe
the cold showering groups
chose to skip work less
for some reason.
It's not clear, but at least
it didn't seem to show
cold showering was harmful
to immune function
at least in the short-run
in healthy adults.